Scottish mss., 1500-1707 LMC 2447
Lilly Library
Scottish mss.
1500-1707
Lilly Library
LMC 2447
2 Boxes 2 standard
4 bound
The Scottish mss., 1500-1707, consists of materials concerned with the genealogies, history, letters, and writings of Scotland.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 1982
Historical Note
The name 'Scotland' derives from the Latin Scotia, 'land of the Scots.' The Scots were a Celtic people from Ireland who settled on the west coast of Great Britain about the 5th century. In 1707, Scotland merged with England to form the United Kingdom of Great Britain.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of legal documents, genealogical materials, histories, and other works relating to Scotland during the 16th-18th centuries.
Note on Indexing Term - "Science": Of interest: His Booke of Arithmeticke and Algebra written by John Napier, baron of Merchiston and the inventor of logarithms.
Authors, Scottish; genealogy; Science; Scotland--History
- L'Oregine de la famille des Stuart est représentée en l'histoire de Joannes Lesley Scotus, episcopus Rossensis..., 16th century -; Document 10 p. 35 cm. (Box 1)
  General
  On cover leaf, bound in at back: Mémoire généalogique des Stuarts
  Last page cut in half: measures ca. 15/16 cm.
  Material drawn from works by John Leslie, bishop of Ross, 1527-1597, De origine moribus et rebus gestis Scotorum, Romae, 1578 (Lilly DA775 .L63 vault); by Robert Gaguin, 1433-1501, French priest and scholar; and by Nicole Gilles, -1503, chronicler and annalist
  Accompanied by later transcription in ink, 15 p., 31 cm., in separte folder
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchase. K.D. Duval, Frenich, Foss, Pitlochry, Perthshire, Scotland. 1983.
- Balcanquhall, Walter, 1586?-1645, royalist. Edinburgh...the Statuts and Ordinances of the Hospitall founded...upon the only charges of the right worshipfull George Heriot..., 13 July 1627 -; Contemporary copy of document 11 p. 30 cm. (Box 1)
  Sewn
  Name in heading given as: Walter Balcanquell; name at end given as: Gualtovus Balcanquell
  Twenty-three chapters containing the rules for the hospital founded from the estate of jeweler George Heriot, 1563-1624, for the education of poor fatherless boys
  Watermark: horn in shield, 7.3 x 5.2 cm.
- Manorial court roll bearing the transumption of sasine from john Urquhart to Sirt John Urquhart and his grandmother Issobelle Irving of Cromarty, Scotland, May-Aug., 1655., Document 666" x 12" (Bound Bound)
  Case label reads "John Urquhart, Cromarty, 1655"
  Reinforced on verso with Japanese tissue
  Purchase. Rick Grunder Books, 915 Maxwell Terrace, Bloomington, Indiana 47401. 1981.
- Urquhart, Sir John. Concurrent rental agreement to George Stewart of Culphin and Janet Barclay, his wife., 1655 -; Document 109 x 30 cm. (Flat Map Case)
  Signed several times by Urquhart, George Stewart, and by witnesses and notaries.
  Between sheets of archival acetate, sealed at edges
- Hope, John, 1650-1682, M.P. for Scotland. Preparations for mines of gold, etc. [Collected notes on gold and silver mines, chiefly in Scotland.], April 1674 -; Autograph document signed 91 p. 15.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  Inscribed in front: From page 1 to page 88 are severall things wch I caused copie out of some papers & manuscripts of Captain David Achesones, at Tyninghame Aprill 1674. John Hope pages 1-84 (43-46, blank) contain references to material dated 1607-1609 and to the year 1619 (page 21
  Pages 84-88 refer to the working of gold, silver, or copper by quicksilver and the toxicity of quicksilver "according to Antonio [Diez?] de Carces as he practised in the Indies at [Potosi?] the space of 25 years"
  Pages 88-91 provide "receipts" for making ink from cherry or plum stones and for making quicksilver to act upon metal
  Volume bears the bookplate of the Hope family
  See Douglas, Peerage of Scotland, Edinburgh, 1813, Second edition, I:741-751 and Plate IX (Lilly CS468 .D736 1813)
- Stair, Sir James Dalrymple, 1st viscount, 1619-1695, lawyer, statesman. Edinburgh. The Forme of Processe, Before the Lords of Council and Session., 1674-27 September 1675 -; Autograph document signed 471 p. 16.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  On spine: The Form of Processe. Dalrymple
  Pages 1-114, The Form of Processe; in two hands
  Several blank pages
  Pages 127-467, [Compilation of legal cases and acts]; in several hands, covering material dated 1546-1639, arranged generally in alphabetical order, e.g., Contracts and Obligations, Divorcement, Marriage, Probate, Rental, Successors & Succession, Tutors & Curators, Writs and Evidence
  Some of the material in Latin
  Certain wise sayings on pages 115, 124, & 471
  Volume bears the library shelfmark of Cortachy Castle, seat of the Oglivy's of Airlie
  Two other manuscripts by Stair, entitled The Forme of Processe, dated 1666 and 17th cent., are located in University of Edinburgh Library. See Edinburgh University Library, Index to Manuscripts (G.K. Hall, Boston, 1964), II:544, and G.K. Hall, Boston, 1981), page 533 (Lilly Z6621 .E26 and Suppl.)
- Perth, James Drummond, 4th Earl and 1st titular Duke, 1648-1716, chancellor of Scotland. Edinburgh. To "My Lord." His presence is required "in matters of great importance which concern the Royall government" on December 30., 20 December 1684 -; Autograph letter signed 1 p. 15 cm. (Box 1)
- Letters to The Laird of Clunie Macpherson., 3 May 1689-20 October 1690 -; Autograph letters signed 28 p. 15.5-31 cm. (Box 1)
  Twenty-one letters addressed to Duncan Macpherson of Clunie, -1721 or 1722, during the struggle between the forces of James II of England and those of William and Mary in Scotland
  Several retain portions of the red wax seal
  Contents: Alexander Canan [i.e. Cannon], colonel - 1689, July 4, 20, and Dec. 23; 1690, Jan. 29 and May 27. John Graham of Claverhouse, 1st viscount Dundee, 1649?-1689, general - 1689, May 19 and July 14, 18, 19?, 20, 22, 26. James Seton, 4th Earl Dunfermline, -1694, army officer - 1689, May 3; 1690, Apr. 5, 20, and May 27. Hugh Mackay, 1640?1692, general - 1689, May 6, 21; 1690, June 27 and Oct. 20. Sir Thomas Livingstone, 1st viscount Teviot, 1652?-1711, army officer - 1690, May 6.
  All letters published in Transactions of the Gaelic Society of Inverness, Vol. 20, pages 221-236, as "Gleanings from the Charter Chest at Cluny Castle" by Mr. Alex. Macpherson of Kingussie (Inverness, The Gaelic Society of Inverness, 1897); except the first four lines of May 21, 1689, and the address portion of June 27, 1690, letters from Mackay; facsimile of the July 26, 1689, letter of Dundee appears as frontispiece.
- ...Company Tradeing to Affrica & the Indies; We the subscribers do each of us for himself...become obliged for the payment of the respective sums by us severally subscribed... Att London., 6-14 November 1695 -; Document 12 p. 47.5 x 34.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  In brown slipcase
  Names and sums of money, led by the name of William Paterson, 1658-1719, banker, of 246 merchants, apothecaries, haberdashers, drapers, and those of some 19 other occupations, including six women, who subscribed for the founding of the Scots' colony on the Isthmus of Darien
  Subscription book formally opened on Nov. 6, 1695, according to George Pratt Insh, The Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies, Charles Scribners, London, 1932 (Main F2281 .D2 I5) on page 47
  Names listed herein do not appear on the list of subscribers published on pages 225-284 of James Samuel Barbour, A History of William Paterson and the Darien Company, William Blackwood and Sons, Edinburgh and London, 1907 (Lily F2281 .D2 B2)
  Bears the bookplate of Sir James Montgomery, Bart. of Stanhope
- Steuart, Jacob. Tractatus Metaphysicus and other works., 1699-23 April 1700 -; Autograph document signed 95 leaves 20 cm. (Bound Bound)
  In Latin in several hand styles
  Initials I S in blind on front and back covers
  On leaf 95 and others: Ex libris Jacobi Steuart
  Other names inscribed in volume: Adam Steuart, James Steuart 1704, Mary Steuart, Robert Steuart
  Heavily marked with decorative devices, names, and various lines of philosophical prose
  Contents: Tractatus Metaphysicus, leaves 3-35; Pneumatologia, leaves 36-56; Elementa philosophiae moralis, leaves 57-70; Tractatus Logicus, leaves 71-89; King Charles His Speech made upon the scafold...tuesday the 30 of Janry 1649 [not a speech, but an account of the event], leaf 90; Summa questiones physicae quae..., leaves 94-93v.
- Perth, James Drummond, earl, -1611. Discharge to Sir John Drummond of sums and dutie due as tenant of Burnebank., 17th century -; Autograph document signed 1 p. 33 cm. (Box 1)
  Signed by Perth, Drummond, and four witnesses
  James Drummond was created 1st Earl Perth in 1605
  Watermark: Foolscap, 14 x 8 cm.
- Ferguson, Adam Crathie, Scotland. The righteous is more Excellent than his Neighbour. Prov. XII, 26 [Collection of essays based on passages from the Bible]., 17 August 1701-20 March 1709 -; Autograph document signed 352+2 p. 20 cm. (Bound Bound)
  Inscribed inside front cover: Ex libris Adami Fergussone
  Inclusive dates found on pages 1 and 236
  Other dates written inside the cover and on Fergusson genealogy page: 1685, 1723, 1736, 1742, 1747
  Fergusson genealogy page lists the birth and baptismal dates, with presiding ministers, of the nine children of Adam Ferguson and Mary Gordon, including that of Adam Ferguson, 1723-1816, philosopher and historian
- List of them who resaved mony from the earel of Glasgow for caring on the union which money was remitted down to the Ld Earel he deponing on the depursments as is here in expressed., 1707 -; Document 1 p. 23 cm. (Box 1)
  List of 32 names who received money from David Boyle, Earl of Glasgow ( -1733), to vote for the Union of Scotland and England
  names and sums of money published, but not in the same order, in George Lockhart of Carnwath, Memoirs concerning the Affairs of Scotland..., The Second Edition, London, Printed by J. Baker, 1714 (Lilly DA805 .L816 M5 1714a) on pages 414-415
- Crawford's Collection of Papers Concerning Scotland. Collected from Originals in the Cottonian Library., Undated -; Document 3 volumes 36.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  Title taken from spine
  Inscribed in each vol: Montrose, 18 October 1782, Presented to Lord Gardenston's publick Library at Laurencekirk by Tho Stewart
  Contents: Vol. 1, 1558-1569, 347 pages plus 9 pages Index; Vol. 2, 1570-1586, 392 pages plus 11 pages Index; Vol. 3, 1567-1586, 296 pages plus 8 pages Index
  Contents cited as whether copied from the original or transcription in the Caligua press of the library of Sir John Cotton (heir of Sir Robert Bruce Cotton, 1571-1631, antiquary)
  Occasional corrections or additions in three other hands
  Two other Crawford collections of papers from the Cottonian Library, located in the Advocates' Library at Edinburgh, described in Sir John Skelton, Maitland of Lethington, William Blackwood & Sons, Edinburgh, 1887 (Main DA787 .M2 S6), Vol. 1, pages xv-xx: one, transcribed chiefly by Robert Robertson, "admirable calligrapher," in 1707 for David Crawford of Drumsoy, in 3 vols.; the other, "extremely illegible," transcribed by Matthew Crawford, Regius Professor of Church History at the University of Edinburgh, assisted by Thomas Baker, in 1725-1728, in 2 vols.
  Both sets contain letters by the same individuals as in this present set: i.e., "Mary, Elizabeth, Cecil, Sadler, Lethington, Randolph, Throckmorton, and Knollys"
- Napier, John, 1550-1617, baron of Merchiston, inventor of logarithms. His booke of Arithmeticke and Algebra., Undated -; Document 137 p. 20.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  In Latin
  Transcription in the hand of Napier's son, Robert Napier, 1580-1655?, for Henry Briggs, 1651-1630, professor of Geometry at Oxford
  Explanatory note, dated 1801, by Francis Napier, the 7th Lord Napier, 1758-1823, concerning the manuscript precedes the text
  Bookplate of the Napier family: See Douglas, Peerage of Scotland, II: Plage XIII (Lilly CS468 .D736 1813)
  Published as De Arte Logistica, edited with an introductory essay by Mark Napier, Edinburgh, 1839 (Lilly QA33 .N19)
- Of all the worthies that advanced the cause... [first line]., Undated -; Document 15 p. 18.5 cm. (Box 1)
  Contemporary verses honoring "...my Lord...thy name shall be blyssed with a happie Immortalitie...And crying Orphans echoe furth thy name."
  Concerns the political and religious situation in Scotland, with references to William and Mary, the English Church, Sir John Dalrymple, and concluding: "And leave the rest to clark John Spading."
  Final set of 14 verses in a different hand, each four line stanza with the same last line: "Hes wiser than I can tell" or a slight variation thereof
  Fastened with two unrusted pins
  Watermark: Pot (5.5 x 4 cm., excluding flower top)
- A Plan of the Harbour and Parts adjacent where the Scotch Company were settled, upon the Isthmus of Darien., Undated -; Document 1 leaf 35.5 x 51 cm. (Flat Map Case)
  Mainland portion entitled: Caledonia
  Fortified location: New Edenbourg
  In the foreground: Goldn Island
  Site of the venture of the Company of Scotland trading to Africa and the Indies between 1698 and 1700
  Closely resembles but not identical to plan published in James Samuel Barbour, A History of William Paterson and the Darien Company, William Blackwood and Sons, Edinburgh and London, 1907 (Lilly F2281 .D2 B2) between pages 66-67
- Scotch Pedigree., Undated -; Document 103 p. 32 cm. (Bound Bound)
  Title taken from spine; internal titles: Scotch Genealogies
  In two parts: p. 1-64 and 1-39, with contents page for each
  First page bears the name of William Shaw Mason, 1774-1853, statist
  Largely in same hand with occasional dates added later in another hand
  Earliest and latest dates for genealogical lines: 1057 to 1758, with some mention of the first century
  Content names about ninety family lines and include the following references: Land measurement by falcon flying, I, 28; Macbeth, king of Scotland, d. 1057, I, 42; John Napier of logarithm fame, 1576-1645, II, 2; Kerr family, II, 13; Sir William Alexander, 1568-1640, dramatic writer and grantee of New Scotland in America, II, 27; David Boyle, Earl of Glasgow, d. 1733, II, 34; and the Battle of Flodden throughout
  Watermark: Pro Patria, with GR countermark
  Bookplate of P.W. Kerr
  Purchase. Elkin Mathews Ltd., Takeley, Bishops Stortford. England. 1983.
- Sibbald, Sir Robert, 1641-1722, physician. The Description and historie of the Sheriffdome of Fyffe and Kinross Shyre., Undated -; Autograph document signed 286 p. 33.5 cm. (Bound Bound)
  Several pages of ca. 29-30 cm. inserted
  Latest internal date: 1692
  In English and Latin
  Contents (or references found therein): 1 - [Dedication] To the Right Honourable John Earle of Rothess Honourable Sheryff of Fyffe. 2 - Blank. 3 - To the Reader. 11 - The account of the ms. and the printed Books made use of in compiling this Treatise. 12 - Blank. 13 - The Description and Historie... 93 - De Fundatoribus Academia et collegiorum in universitate Andreapolitana. 108 - Bishops of St. Andrews. 144 - Arthur Johnstone, 1587-1644, verse writer. 156 - Sir James balfour, 1600-1657, historian and passim. 160 - George Buchanan, 1506-1582, historian; "The coal burns yet...". 197 - John Johnstone, 1570?-1611, poet. 210 - Alexander Scott, 1525?-1584?, poet. 218 - Blank. 236 - Account of the damps and "smoak" arising from the cannel coal pits "visible in the form...of a football" and "the workman is sensible of a difficulty of breathing." 239 - Concerning the encroachment of ye sea on severla parts in the shyre. 240 - Blank. 243 - Account of the fishes and aquatick animals the shyre may be furnished with... 251 - "the publick librarie at St. Andrews containeth many choise books"... 252 - The titles of the several parts, sections and chapters of this treatise. 255 - Index of the ancient charters & papers whereof the copies are in this treatise, ending with the Bulla Gregory XI contra regaliam. 261 - Ms. in 16th century hand with HAND watermark. 263 - The Index of the Principall matters contained in this treatise. 286 - X Y Z [no entries].
  Bookplate: The Arms of Dundas of Armiston
  Varies somewhat from Sibbald's The History of Fife and Kinross, published at Edinburgh in 1710 (Lilly DA880 .F4 S56)